<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/esr2html.xsl"?>

<ESR xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/esr" name="Operating System Fundamentals">

	<intro>
		<esrtitle>Operating System Fundamentals</esrtitle>
		<maintainer>National Information Assurance Partnership and Communications-Electronics Security Group</maintainer>
		<identifier>42</identifier>
		<version>0.1</version>
		<status>draft</status>
		<issuedate>1 April 2015</issuedate>
		<approver></approver>
		<supercedes></supercedes>
	</intro>

    <section title="Background and Purpose" id="purpose">
	<!-- This section sets the context for not only the ESR, but what is expected of
	the resulting Protection Profile (PP). The intent is that the remaining
	sections provide succinct statements that highlight the relevant aspects to
	be addressed by the Technical Community (TC) constructing the PP. Here, the
	authors provide a narrative that introduces the reader to the problem being
	solved, and presents key aspects that support or guide the TC, and may
	elaborate on subtleties not apparent in the “bulleted” high level
	statements.-->
	An operating system is software that manages computer hardware and software
	resources and provides common services for application programs.  The hardware
	it manages may be physical or virtual.
	<p/>
	The document describes the high-level security requirements for a
	general-purpose operating system (OS).  The requirements are targeted at
	mitigating well-defined threats.  Furthermore, the ESR establishes a scope
	that informs development of the requirements, based on use cases and
	environmental assumptions.  In addition to stating what properties an OS
	must minimally exhibit, the ESR also describes functionality that vendors
	should consider as an extension, but goes beyond the expected minimal
	baseline. 
	<p/>
	This scoping enables delivery of an effective set of security functional
	requirements in the PP, as well as the evaluation activities
	performed during the course of evaluation. It ensures that
	objective and repeatable evaluation activities can be captured in the PP
	while still delivering a PP in a timely manner. Another factor is to
	ensure the security functionality prescribed is realistic and 
	can be achieved by commercially-available products.  
	</section>

    <section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">
	<i>This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the security
	problem by providing the reader with concise statements regarding the
	scenarios in which the technology is being used. The intended usage
	presented here should lay the groundwork for the identifying the resources
	to be protected, and what threats must be considered in the drafting of the
	Essential Security Requirements (ESR) and for the TC to consider when
	writing the PP.  </i>
	</section>

    <section title="Resources to be protected" id="resourcesprotected">
	<i>This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the security
	problem by providing the reader with concise statements regarding the
	scenarios in which the technology is being used. The intended usage
	presented here should lay the groundwork for the identifying the resources
	to be protected, and what threats must be considered in the drafting of the
	Essential Security Requirements (ESR) and for the TC to consider when
	writing the PP.  </i>
	</section>

    <section title="Attacker access" id="attackeraccess">
	<i>Here the author provides the threat paths that the requirements need to
	address and mitigate. This includes the type of access an attacker may have
	to target. This would include whether there is a concern regarding remote
	or local access to the target, or whether there are special concerns
	regarding physical access.</i>
	</section>

    <section title="Essential Security Requirements" id="requirements">
	<i>This is where the authors present an initial set of English requirements
	that specify security functionality, rather than design and/or
	implementation characteristics. These requirements will provide the
	foundation for which the detailed set of requirements is derived. It is
	important that the requirements captured here make an attempt to fully
	address the categories (e.g., access control, identification and
	authentication, management capabilities, roles of administration, secure
	communications, and audit). That's not to say the requirements are fully
	specified or detailed enough to simply translate to Common Criteria
	security functional requirements. The goal is that there is enough
	information contained here, as well as the other sections of this document,
	to provide the TC enough information to ensure they have an understanding
	of what is minimally required in breath.</i>
	</section>

    <section title="Assumptions" id="assumptions">
	<!--Simply put, this section presents the aspects of the product and its
	intended environment that can be assumed to hold true. This will provide
	additional scope on the resulting PP. -->
	The following assumptions are made for the operating system product and
	its operational environmental:
	<ul>
	<li>The OS implements some security-relevant functionality which does
	not require evaluation.  Examples include network time synchronization, process scheduling, and virtual
	memory management (to include process separation).
	</li>
	<li>The capability of the OS to be managed by the enterprise is optional.
	Enterprise management does not increase or decrease overall risk exposure.
	Enterprise management, if supported, represents an operational choice.
	</li>
	<li>The capability of the OS to bind to directory services is optional.
	Binding to directory services does not increase or decrease overall risk
	exposure.  Binding to directory services, if supported, represents an
	operational choice.  When it is not bound to directory services, the OS
	provides login for only a single user, or a very limited number of users.
	</li>
	<li>Administrators are not malicious in nature.
	</li>
	<li>Users are not malicious in nature.
	</li>
	</ul>
	</section>


    <section title="Optional Extensions (optional)" id="extensions">
	Additional security functionality that may be appropriate for some
	use cases, and can be expressed in extensions to this document, includes:
	<ul>
	<li>Multi-level Security (MLS) access controls</li>
	<li>Attestation of security measurements</li>
	<li>Data-at-rest protection - already covered in other PPs</li>
	<li>IPSec VPNs - already covered in other PPs</li>
	</ul>
	</section>

    <section title="Outside the TOE's Scope (optional)" id="outsidescope">
	This is where the authors explicitly state things they do not want to be
	considered for inclusion in an evaluation against a resulting PP.  Items
	expressed here could include threats, functions or capabilities that would
	require assurance activities that are too subjective, or specific expertise
	not available in the evaluation facilities expected to assess products
	against the PP (e.g., assessing anti-tamper measures).
	</section>

</ESR>
