<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/esr2html.xsl"?>

<ESR xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/esr" name="Operating System Fundamentals">

	<intro>
		<esrtitle>Operating System Fundamentals</esrtitle>
		<maintainer>National Information Assurance Partnership (US) and Communications-Electronics Security Group (UK)</maintainer>
		<identifier>42</identifier>
		<version>0.1</version>
		<status>draft</status>
		<issuedate>1 April 2015</issuedate>
		<approver></approver>
		<supercedes></supercedes>
	</intro>

    <section title="Background and Purpose" id="purpose">
	<!-- This section sets the context for not only the ESR, but what is expected of
	the resulting Protection Profile (PP). The intent is that the remaining
	sections provide succinct statements that highlight the relevant aspects to
	be addressed by the Technical Community (TC) constructing the PP. Here, the
	authors provide a narrative that introduces the reader to the problem being
	solved, and presents key aspects that support or guide the TC, and may
	elaborate on subtleties not apparent in the “bulleted” high level
	statements.-->
	An operating system is software that manages computer hardware and software
	resources, and provides common services for application programs.  The hardware
	it manages may be physical or virtual.  
	<p/>
	This essential security requirements (ESR) document outlines the high-level
	security requirements for a general-purpose operating system (OS), which will
	be expressed in a Common Criteria Protection Profile (PP).  These
	requirements address threats within a scope established by use cases and
	environment assumptions.  In addition to stating what properties an OS must
	minimally exhibit, this document also identifies functionality that vendors
	should consider as extensions that go beyond the expected minimal baseline,
	and which may be appropriate in more-specific use cases. 
	<p/>
	The security functionality must be realistic and achievable by
	commercially-available products.  The resulting PP will also include objective and
	repeatable evaluation activities, so that evaluations can be executed in a
	manner that tracks with industry's release of operating system products.
	<p/>
	With regard to evaluation scope, the operating system itself is composed of the
	software that is delivered to the end user in the operating system product.
	This typically includes a kernel and drivers that run with elevated
	privileges, common software libraries, and a great deal of application
	software which runs with varying levels of privileges.  Many of these
	applications provide security services and are an essential part of the
	operating system product.  However, applications which are covered by
	more-specific Protection Profiles should not be claimed to be evaluated as
	part of the OS evaluation, even when it is necessary to evaluate some of
	their functionality as it relates to their role as part of the OS.
	</section>

    <section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">
      <p> 
	The OS is installed on a platform to allocate platform resources among applications.
	This includes several use cases in which the OS acts as a platform for applications:
	<ul>
	<li>End user systems such as a desktop or laptop, which is optionally bound to a directory server or management server</li>
	<li>Server systems, running on physical or virtual hardware</li>
	<li>Cloud systems, running on virtual hardware</li>
	</ul>
      </p>
	<!-- <i>This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the security -->
	<!-- problem by providing the reader with concise statements regarding the -->
	<!-- scenarios in which the technology is being used. The intended usage -->
	<!-- presented here should lay the groundwork for the identifying the resources -->
	<!-- to be protected, and what threats must be considered in the drafting of the -->
	<!-- Essential Security Requirements (ESR) and for the TC to consider when -->
	<!-- writing the PP.  </i> -->
	</section>

    <section title="Resources to be protected" id="resourcesprotected">
	<p>
	<ul>	
	<li>Platform hardware resources managed by the OS (e.g. network
	interfaces, microphones, and storage media).</li>
	<li>Sensitive user data (e.g. home directories).</li>
	<li>Sensitive system data (e.g. account information, audit files, configuration files).
	</li>
	<li>Resources that compromise the OS itself, upon which its integrity
	depends.  This includes files such as the kernel and its drivers,
	privileged applications which provide services to other applications, and
	shared software libraries.
	</li>
	</ul>	
	</p>
	<!-- <i>This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the security -->
	<!-- problem by providing the reader with concise statements regarding the -->
	<!-- scenarios in which the technology is being used. The intended usage -->
	<!-- presented here should lay the groundwork for the identifying the resources -->
	<!-- to be protected, and what threats must be considered in the drafting of the -->
	<!-- Essential Security Requirements (ESR) and for the TC to consider when -->
	<!-- writing the PP.  </i> -->
	</section>

    <section title="Attacker access" id="attackeraccess">
	The following assumptions are made about attackers' ability to develop
	attacks:
	<ul>
	<li>An attacker has an arbitrary amount of time to analyze the behavior of
	the OS, its interaction with its platform, and the data it transmits over
	the network.</li>
	<li>An attacker is able to acquire their own copy of the target OS and
	study its behavior on a platform that they control.</li>
	</ul>
	<p/>
	The attacker is expected to engage in the following general classes of attack:
	<!-- added in order to allow for rather direct flow to Threats section in PP -->
	<ul>
	<li>Network eavesdropping, in which an attacker may monitor and gain access
	to data exchanged between the OS and other endpoints.</li>
	<li>Network attack, in which an attacker may initiate malicious communications with the
	OS or alter communications between the OS and other endpoints.</li>
	<li>Local attack, in which an attacker has gained the ability to execute code on the system,
	which may be used to escalate privilege or access data without authorization.
	</li>
	<li>Limited physical access attack, in which an attacker may attempt to access
	data on the system by virtue of being physically present for a limited
	period of time.  This limited physical access does not include attacks in
	which the attacker could disassemble the system to gain access to its
	storage media or manipulate the OS's underlying platform. 
	
	Systems used for remote working, such as laptops and tablets,
	for which an attacker could gain longer physical access to, should
	apply additional protections which are provided by products evaluated against other
	Protection Profiles (e.g. FDE cPP).
	</li>
	<li>Persistence, in which an attacker has already exploited the system and wishes
	to maintain presence on the system.</li>
	</ul>
    </section>

    <section title="Essential Security Requirements" id="requirements">
      <!--
        <i>This is where the authors present an initial set of English requirements
	that specify security functionality, rather than design and/or
	implementation characteristics. These requirements will provide the
	foundation for which the detailed set of requirements is derived. It is
	important that the requirements captured here make an attempt to fully
	address the categories (e.g., access control, identification and
	authentication, management capabilities, roles of administration, secure
	communications, and audit). That's not to say the requirements are fully
	specified or detailed enough to simply translate to Common Criteria
	security functional requirements. The goal is that there is enough
	information contained here, as well as the other sections of this document,
	to provide the TC enough information to ensure they have an understanding
	of what is minimally required in breath. </i>
-->


	<p>
	  The following are the essential security requirements expected 
	  to be implemented by an operating system within the established scope:
	<ul>
	  <li>
	    implement modern anti-exploitation features, these include, but are not limited to 
	    Address Space Layer Randomization (ASLR), 
	    Stack Canaries/Cookies, and Data Execution Protection (DEP) to protect 
	    itself and its applications.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    provide the following cryptographic services:
	    <ul>
	      <li>Asymmetric key generation</li>
	      <li>Symmetric key encryption and decryption </li>
	      <li>Deterministic random bit generation (DRBG)</li>
	      <li>Cryptographic hashing </li>
	      <li>Cryptographic signing</li>
	      <li>Keyed-hash message authentication</li>
	      <li>TLS support</li>
	    </ul>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    provide a trusted update mechanism to update itself, applications, and,
	    optionally, firmware for the platform it runs on.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    provide strong authentication mechanisms.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    leverage a trusted or secure boot process.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	  	provide the ability to whitelist application execution
	  </li>
	  <li> 
		provide the ability to control external interfaces
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    audit security-relevant events and provide mechanism for secure transmission of audit data.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    provide mechanisms for management by the user and enterprise, to include optionally binding to:
		<ul>
		<li>directory servers, which provide support for multi-user login and sophisticated password policies</li>
		<li>management servers, which provide support for applying enterprise security policies</li>
		</ul>
	  </li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	</section>

    <section title="Assumptions" id="assumptions">
	<!--Simply put, this section presents the aspects of the product and its
	intended environment that can be assumed to hold true. This will provide
	additional scope on the resulting PP. -->
	The following assumptions are made for the operating system product and
	its operational environmental:
	<ul>
	<li>The underlying platform is physically protected, to a large extent. The hardware that the OS 
	manages is secured by defensive measures that make physical
	attacks impractical for most attackers.  At the same time, casual passersby might
	attempt to trivially access the system.
	</li>
	<li>The OS implements some security-relevant functionality which does
	not require evaluation (e.g., network time synchronization, process scheduling, and virtual
	memory management including process separation).
	</li>
	<li>Depending on configuration and capability, the OS may or may not be:
	<ul>
	<li>configuration-managed by the enterprise</li>
	<li>bound to directory services to support multi-user login</li>
	These do not fundamentally increase or decrease overall risk
	exposure, and represent operational choices.
	</ul>
	</li>
	<li>The OS runs application software developed by a third-party.
	The applications are not intentionally developed to be malicious, but can
	contain inadvertent coding errors.
	</li>
	<li>The platform is connected to a network. 
	For purposes of sending/receiving data, to include software updates, 
	the platform is connected to other entities.
	Other entities on the network are not inherently trustable.
	</li>
	<li>Administrators are not malicious in nature.</li>
	<li>Users are not malicious in nature.</li>
	</ul>
	</section>


    <section title="Optional Extensions (optional)" id="extensions">
	Additional security functionality that may be appropriate for some
	use cases, and can be expressed in extensions to this document, includes:
	<ul>
	<li>Multi-level Security (MLS) access controls</li>
	<li>Attestation of security measurements</li>
	<li>Data-at-rest protection - already covered in other PPs</li>
	<li>IPSec VPNs - already covered in other PPs</li>
	</ul>
	</section>

    <section title="Outside the TOE's Scope (optional)" id="outsidescope">
	<!--This is where the authors explicitly state things they do not want to be
	considered for inclusion in an evaluation against a resulting PP.  Items
	expressed here could include threats, functions or capabilities that would
	require assurance activities that are too subjective, or specific expertise
	not available in the evaluation facilities expected to assess products
	against the PP (e.g., assessing anti-tamper measures). -->
	The following list contains items which are explicitly out-of-scope for any evaluation against the OS PP
    <ul>
    	<li>Malicious, Highly-Privileged Administrators - 
	Highly-privileged administrators acting maliciously can disable most, 
	if not all, security protections on the OS. 
	Additionally procedural controls which are out of scope of this document should be
	considered to help highlight administrator accounts acting suspiciously.</li>
    	<li>Zero Days - The disclosure of recently published vulnerabilities (Zero Days)
	should not be used as a reason to fail an OS undergoing evaluation.</li>
    	<li>Unofficial Versions - Non-vendor supplied install images often contain 
	added functionality and may weaken the normal operating functionality of the OS</li>
    	<li>Platform - The OS PP shall not address the hardware or firmware of the underlying platform
	to include the boot sequence before control is handed off to the OS. That the platform itself
	is virtual or physical is irrelevant to any evaluations.
    	</li>
    	<li>Applications - The OS PP shall not address applications that are not 
	delivered as part of the OS normal installation 
    	to include privileged apps that alter the behavior of the delivered OS.
    	</li>
    </ul>
    </section>
</ESR>
