<ns0:Package xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:ns0="https://niap-ccevs.org/cc/v1" xmlns:ns1="https://niap-ccevs.org/cc/v1/section" name="Secure Shell">

  <ns0:project-notes>
   This update turns the SSH Extended Package into a Functional Package. 
   This branch incorporates the CCUF version of the SSH FP into the NIAP version.

   Significant changes:

	- Removed FCS_COP and required that the PP or PP-Module that includes the package support the required algorithms. This effectively 
		eliminated the need for TD0240.
	- Incorporated TD0331
	- Incorporated TD0332
	- Incorporated TD0420
	- Incorporated TD0446
	- Added audit events covering those specified in NDcPP and a couple of the ESM PPs. These are presented as optional, and can be
		incoporated by selection in a PP or PP-module that includes this package. (TLS should do this too).   
 </ns0:project-notes>

  <ns0:PPReference>
   <ns0:ReferenceTable>
      <ns0:PPTitle>Functional Package for Secure Shell (SSH)</ns0:PPTitle>
      <ns0:PPVersion>1.0</ns0:PPVersion>
      <ns0:PPAuthor>National Information Assurance Partnership</ns0:PPAuthor>
      <ns0:PPPubDate>2021-05-13</ns0:PPPubDate>
      <ns0:Keywords>SSH; secure shell</ns0:Keywords>
    </ns0:ReferenceTable>
  </ns0:PPReference>
  
  <ns0:RevisionHistory>
    <ns0:entry>
      <ns0:version>1.0</ns0:version>
      <ns0:date>2021-05-13</ns0:date>
      <ns0:subject>Converted SSH EP to a Functional Package and incorporated CCUF CWG input.</ns0:subject>
    </ns0:entry>
  </ns0:RevisionHistory>
	

  <ns0:pp-preferences>

    <ns0:audit-events-in-sfrs />
  </ns0:pp-preferences>

	



<ns1:Introduction>
	



  <ns1:Overview>
        <html:p>
	    Secure Shell (SSH) is a protocol for secure remote login and other secure network services over
	    an untrusted network. SSH software can act as a client, server, or both.
      	</html:p><html:p>
		This <html:i>Functional Package for Secure Shell</html:i> provides a collection of Secure Shell (SSH) protocol related SFRs and 
		Evaluation Activities (EAs) covering audit, authentication, cryptographic algorithms, and protocol negotiation. The intent 
		of this package is to provide PP, cPP, and PP-Module authors with a readily consumable collection of SFRs and EAs to be integrated into
		their documents.  
        </html:p>
   </ns1:Overview>






   <ns0:tech-terms>
	   <ns0:term full="Connection">The SSH transport layer between a client and a server.  Within a connection there can
			be multiple sessions. </ns0:term>
	   <ns0:term full="Rekey">Where the connection renegotiates the shared secret and each session subsequently derives a new 
			encryption key.  </ns0:term>
	   <ns0:term full="Session">A discrete stream of data within a connection.  </ns0:term>
	   <ns0:term abbr="SSH" full="Secure Shell">Cryptographic network protocol for initiating text-based shell sessions
		   on remote systems.</ns0:term>
   </ns0:tech-terms>
	
     



    <ns1:toes title="Compliant Targets of Evaluation">
		<html:p>The Target of Evaluation (TOE) in this Functional Package (FP) is a product which acts as an SSH client, SSH 
	    server, or both. This FP describes the extended security functionality of SSH in terms of <ns0:xref g="CC" />. </html:p>
		<html:p>The contents of this Functional Package must be appropriately incoporated into a PP, cPP, or PP-Module. When this package 
		is so incorporated, the ST must include selection-based requirements in accordance with the selections or assignments 
		indicated in the incorporating document.
		</html:p><html:p>The PP, cPP, or PP-Module that instantiates this Package must typically include the following components in order to satisfy 
		dependencies of this Package. It is the responsibility of the PP, cPP, or PP-Module author who incorporates this FP to 
		ensure that dependence on these components is satisfied, either by the TOE or by assumptions about its Operational Environment.
		</html:p><html:p>An ST must identify the applicable version of the PP, cPP, or PP-Module and this
		Functional Package in its conformance claims.</html:p>
		<ns0:componentsneeded>
			<ns0:componentneeded>
				<ns0:componentid>FCS_CKM.1</ns0:componentid>
				<ns0:notes>To support key generation for SSH, the incoporating document must
					include FCS_CKM.1 and specify the corresponding algorithm(s).</ns0:notes>
			</ns0:componentneeded>
			<ns0:componentneeded>
				<ns0:componentid>FCS_CKM.2</ns0:componentid>
					<ns0:notes>To support key establishment for SSH, the incoporating document must
						include FCS_CKM.2 and specify the corresponding algorithm(s).</ns0:notes>
			</ns0:componentneeded>
			<ns0:componentneeded>
				<ns0:componentid>FCS_COP.1</ns0:componentid>
				<ns0:notes>
					To support the cryptography needed for SSH communications, the incoporating document must include FCS_COP.1 
					(iterating as needed) to specify AES with corresponding key sizes and modes, digital signature generation and 
					verification function (at least one of RSA or ECDSA), a cryptographic hash function, and a keyed-hash message
					authentication function. In particular, the incoporating document must support AES-CTR as defined in NIST SP 800-38A 
					with key sizes of both 128 and 256 bits.
				</ns0:notes>
			</ns0:componentneeded>
			
			<ns0:componentneeded>
				<ns0:componentid>FCS_RBG_EXT.1</ns0:componentid>
				<ns0:notes>To support random bit generation needed for SSH key generation,
					the incorporating document must include a requirement that specifies the TOE's ability to invoke or provide 
					random bit generation services, commonly identified as FCS_RBG_EXT.1.</ns0:notes>
			</ns0:componentneeded>
			<ns0:componentneeded>
				<ns0:componentid>FIA_X509_EXT.1</ns0:componentid>
				<ns0:notes>To support establishment of SSH communications using a public key algorithm that includes X.509, 
					the incorporating document must include FIA_X509_EXT.1. Note however that support for X.509 is selectable 
					and not mandatory.  </ns0:notes>
			</ns0:componentneeded>
			<ns0:componentneeded>
			<ns0:componentid>FIA_X509_EXT.2</ns0:componentid>
				<ns0:notes>To support establishment of SSH communications using a public key algorithm that includes X.509, 
					the incoporating document must include FIA_X509_EXT.2. Note however that support for X.509 is selectable 
					and not mandatory. </ns0:notes>
			</ns0:componentneeded>
			<ns0:componentneeded>
			<ns0:componentid>FPT_STM.1</ns0:componentid>
				<ns0:notes>To support establishment of SSH communications using a public key algorithm that includes X.509, 
					the incorporating document must include FPT_STM.1 or some other requirement that ensures reliable system time.  
					Note however that support for time-based rekey thresholds is selectable and not mandatory.</ns0:notes>
			</ns0:componentneeded>
		</ns0:componentsneeded>
	</ns1:toes>
</ns1:Introduction>
  



<ns1:Conformance_Claims>
      

	  
</ns1:Conformance_Claims>




	



<ns1:Security_Functional_Requirements>

	
	<ns1:ss-audit-table title="Auditable Events for Mandatory SFRs">
		<html:p>
			The auditable events specified in this Package are included in a Security Target 
			if the incorporating PP, cPP, or PP-Module supports audit event reporting through FAU_GEN.1
			and all other criteria in the incorporating PP or PP-Module are met.
		</html:p>
		<ns0:audit-table id="at-man-audit" table="mandatory">
			<html:div class="table-caption"><ns0:ctr ctr-type="Table" id="atref-mandatory">: Auditable Events for Mandatory SFRs</ns0:ctr></html:div>
		</ns0:audit-table>
	</ns1:ss-audit-table>
	  
	
	
	
	<ns1:cryptsup title="Cryptographic Support (FCS)">
	
	
	
	
	
		<ns0:f-component cc-id="fcs_ssh_ext.1" name="SSH Protocol">
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e1">
				<ns0:title>The TOE shall implement <html:i>SSH</html:i> acting as a
					<ns0:selectables>
						<ns0:selectable id="ssh-client">client</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="ssh-server">server</ns0:selectable>
					</ns0:selectables> in accordance with
				that complies with RFCs 4251, 4252, 4253, 4254,
					<ns0:selectables>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc4256">4256</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc4344">4344</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc5647">5647</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc5656">5656</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc6187">6187</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc6668">6668</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc8268">8268</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc8308">8308</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc8332">8332</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc8709">8709</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable id="sel-rfc8731">8731</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable exclusive="yes">no other RFCs</ns0:selectable>
					</ns0:selectables> and [<html:i>no other standard</html:i>].
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:note role="application">
					The following mapping is provided as a guide to ST authors to ensure the appropriate RFC selections are made 
					based on applicable selections in subsequent SFRs: 
					<html:ul>
						<html:li>RFC 4256: Select for keyboard-interactive authentication </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 4344: Select for AES-128-CTR or AES-256-CTR  </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 5647: Select for AEAD_AES_128_GCM, AEAD_AES_256_GCM, or aes*-gcm@openssh.com </html:li> 
						<html:li>RFC 5656: Select for elliptic curve cryptography </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 6187: Select for X.509 certificate use </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 6668: Select for HMAC-SHA-2 algorithms </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 8268: Select for FFC DH groups with SHA-2  </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 8308: Select if RFC 8332 is selected </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 8332: Select if SHA-2 is available with ssh-rsa </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 8709: Select if ed25519 or ed448 is used as a public key algorithm </html:li>
						<html:li>RFC 8731: Select if curve25519 or curve448 is used for key exchange </html:li> 
					</html:ul>
					<html:p>The ST author selects which of the additional RFCs to which
					conformance is being claimed. An SSH product can implement additional RFCs, but only those
					listed in the selection can be claimed as conformant under CC. 
					The RFC selections for this requirement must be consistent with selections in
					later elements of this Functional Package (e.g., cryptographic algorithms permitted). </html:p>

					<html:p>For the purposes of this package (and subsequent integration into cPPs) only the claimed algorithms listed 
					in the package must be enabled for use.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 4253 indicates that certain cryptographic algorithms are "REQUIRED." This means that from the 
					Internet Engineering Task Force's (IETF's) perspective the implementation must include support, not that the algorithms must 
					be enabled for use. For the purposes of this SFR's evaluation activity and this Functional Package
					overall, it is not necessary to ensure that algorithms listed as "REQUIRED" by the RFC 
					but not listed in later elements of this Functional Package are actually implemented.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 4344 must be selected if aes128-ctr or aes256-ctr is selected in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.4.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 4356 must be selected if "keyboard-interactive" is selected in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.2.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 5647 must be selected when AEAD_AES_128_GCM, AEAD_AES_256_GCM, aes128-gcm@openssh.com, or
					aes256-gcm@openssh.com is selected as an encryption algorithm in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.4 
					and when AEAD_AES_128_GCM or AEAD_AES_256_GCM is selecyed as MAC algorithm in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.5.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 5656 must be selected when ecdsa-sha2-nistp256, ecdsa-sha2-nistp384, ecdsa-sha2-nistp521 is selected as a public key algorithm
					in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.2, or when ecdh-sha2-nistp256, ecdh-sha2-nistp384, or ecdh-sha2-nistp521 is selected
					as a key exchange algorithm in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.6, or when "RFC 5656" is selected in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.7.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 6187 must be selected when x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256, x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp384, x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp521,
					or x509v3-rsa2048-sha256 is selected as a public key algorithm in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.2.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 6668 must be selected when hmac-sha2-256 or hmac-sha2-512 is selected as a MAC algorithm in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.5.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 8268 must be selected when diffie-hellman-group14-sha256, diffie-hellman-group15-sha512,   
						diffie-hellman-group16-sha512, diffie-hellman-group17-sha512, or diffie-hellman-group18-sha512
						is selected as a key exchange algorithm in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.6.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 8332 must be selected when rsa-sha2-256 or rsa-sha2-512 is selected as a public key algorithm in
					FCS_SSH_EXT.1.2.</html:p>

					<html:p>RFC 8709 must be selected when ssh-ed25519 or ssh-ed448 is selected as a public key algorithm in
					FCS_SSH_EXT.1.2.</html:p>
					
					<html:p>RFC 8731 must be selected when curve25519-sha256 or curve448-sha512 is selected as a key exchange 
						algorithm in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.6.</html:p>						

					<html:p>If "client" is selected, then the ST must include FCS_SSHC_EXT.1.</html:p>
					<html:p>If "server" is selected, then the ST must include FCS_SSHS_EXT.1.</html:p>
				</ns0:note>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator shall ensure that the selections indicated in the ST are consistent with selections in this
						and subsequent components. Otherwise, this SFR is evaluated by activities for other SFRs. <html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>
					<ns0:Guidance>
						There are no guidance evaluation activities for this component. This SFR is evaluated by activities for other SFRs.<html:p />
					</ns0:Guidance>
					<ns0:Tests>
						There are no test evaluation activities for this component. This SFR is evaluated by activities for other SFRs.<html:p />
					</ns0:Tests>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e2">
				<ns0:title>
					The TSF shall ensure that the SSH protocol implementation supports the following authentication methods: 
					<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
						<ns0:selectable>“password” (RFC 4252)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>“keyboard-interactive” (RFC 4256)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable>“publickey” (RFC 4252): 
							<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
								<ns0:selectable>ssh-rsa (RFC 4253)</ns0:selectable>  
								<ns0:selectable>rsa-sha2-256 (RFC 8332)</ns0:selectable> 
								<ns0:selectable>rsa-sha2-512 (RFC 8332)</ns0:selectable> 
								<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp256 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>  
								<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp384 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable> 
								<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp521 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>
								<ns0:selectable>ssh-ed25519 (RFC 8709)</ns0:selectable>
								<ns0:selectable>ssh-ed448 (RFC 8709)</ns0:selectable>
								<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable> 
								<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp384 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable> 
								<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp521 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable>
								<ns0:selectable>x509v3-rsa2048-sha256  (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable> 
							</ns0:selectables>
						</ns0:selectable>
					</ns0:selectables> and no other methods.
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:note role="application">
					Within SSH there are two types of authentication: user authentication and peer authentication. This SFR 
					deals with the options supported for user authentication. Peer authentication is covered in
					FCS_SSHS_EXT.1.1 (for servers) and FCS_SSHC_EXT.1.1 (for clients).
				</ns0:note>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator shall check to ensure that the authentication methods listed in the TSS are identical to those
						listed in this SFR component; and, ensure if password-based authentication methods have been selected in the ST 
						then these are also described; and, ensure that if keyboard-interactive is selected, it describes the
						multifactor authentication mechanisms provided by the TOE.<html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>	
					<ns0:Guidance>
						The evaluator shall check the guidance documentation to ensure the configuration options, if any, for
						authentication mechanisms provided by the TOE are described.<html:p />
					</ns0:Guidance>
					<ns0:Tests>
						<ns0:testlist>
							<ns0:test> [conditional] If the TOE is acting as SSH Server: <html:p />
								<html:ol type="a">
									<html:li>The evaluator shall use a suitable SSH Client to connect to the TOE, enable debug messages
										in the SSH Client, and examine the debug messages to determine that only the configured authentication
										methods for the TOE were offered by the server. </html:li>
									<html:li>[conditional] If the SSH server supports X509 based Client authentication options: 
										<html:ol type="a">
											<html:li>The evaluator shall initiate an SSH session from a client where the username is
												associated with the X509 certificate. The evaluator shall verify the session is successfully
												established. </html:li>
											<html:li>Next the evaluator shall use the same X509 certificate as above but include a 
												username not associated with the certificate. The evaluator shall verify that the
												session does not establish.</html:li>
											<html:li>Finally, the evaluator shall use the correct username (from step a above) but use 
												a different X509 certificate which is not associated with the username. The evaluator
												shall verify that the session does not establish. </html:li>
										</html:ol>
									</html:li>
								</html:ol>
							</ns0:test>
							<ns0:test>[conditional] If the TOE is acting as SSH Client, the evaluator shall test for a successful 
								configuration setting of each authentication method as follows:
								<html:ol type="a">
									<html:li>The evaluator shall initiate a SSH session using the authentication method configured and
										verify that the session is successfully established.</html:li>
									<html:li>Next, the evaluator shall use bad authentication data (e.g. incorrectly generated 
										certificate or incorrect password) and ensure that the connection is rejected. </html:li>
								</html:ol>
							  Steps a-b shall be repeated for each independently configurable authentication method supported by the server. 
							</ns0:test>
							<ns0:test>
								[conditional] If the TOE is acting as SSH Client, the evaluator shall verify that the connection
								fails upon configuration mismatch as follows: 
								<html:ol type="a">
									<html:li>The evaluator shall configure the Client with an authentication method not supported by
										the Server.  </html:li>
									<html:li>The evaluator shall verify that the connection fails. </html:li>
								</html:ol>
							</ns0:test>	
						</ns0:testlist>
						If the Client supports only one authentication method, the evaluator can test this failure of connection by
						configuring the Server with an authentication method not supported by the Client. In order to facilitate
						this test, it is acceptable for the evaluator to configure an authentication method that is outside of the 
						selections in the SFR.<html:p />
					</ns0:Tests>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e3">
				<ns0:title>
					The TSF shall ensure that, as described in RFC 4253, packets greater than 
					<ns0:assignable>number of bytes between 35,000 and 1 GB (inclusive)</ns0:assignable>
					in an SSH transport connection are dropped.
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:note role="application">
					RFC 4253 (section 6.1) provides for the acceptance of “large packets” with the caveat that the packets should
					be of “reasonable length” or dropped. The assignment should be filled in by the ST author with the maximum packet 
					size accepted, thus defining “reasonable length” for the TOE. <html:p />
					The upper bound on the packet size is driven by the size identified in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.8.
				</ns0:note>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator shall check that the TSS describes how “large packets” are detected and handled. <html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>
					<ns0:Tests>
						<ns0:testlist>
							<ns0:test>The evaluator shall demonstrate that the TOE accepts the maximum allowed packet size.</ns0:test>
							<ns0:test>This test is performed to verify that the TOE drops packets that are larger than size
								specified in the component.
								<html:ol type="a">
									<html:li>The evaluator shall establish a successful SSH connection with the peer. </html:li> 	
									<html:li>Next the evaluator shall craft a packet that is one byte larger than the maximum
										size specified in this component and send it through the established SSH connection
										to the TOE. </html:li>
									<html:li>Evaluator shall verify that the packet was dropped by the TOE by reviewing the TOE 
										audit log for a dropped packet audit.</html:li>
								</html:ol>
							</ns0:test>
						</ns0:testlist><html:p />
					</ns0:Tests>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e4">
				<ns0:title>
					The TSF shall protect data in transit from unauthorised disclosure using the following mechanisms: 
					<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
						<ns0:selectable>aes128-ctr (RFC 4344)</ns0:selectable>  
						<ns0:selectable>aes256-ctr (RFC 4344)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>aes128-cbc (RFC 4253)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>aes256-cbc (RFC 4253)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>AEAD_AES_128_GCM (RFC 5647)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable>AEAD_AES_256_GCM (RFC 5647)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable>aes128-gcm@openssh.com (RFC 5647)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable>aes256-gcm@openssh.com (RFC 5647)</ns0:selectable>
					</ns0:selectables> and no other mechanisms.
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:note role="application">
					As described in RFC 5647, AEAD_AES_128_GCM and AEAD_AES_256_GCM need the corresponding MAC algorithm to be
					selected in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.5.
				</ns0:note>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator will check the description of the implementation of SSH in the TSS to ensure the encryption
						algorithms supported are specified. The evaluator will check the TSS to ensure that the encryption algorithms
						specified are identical to those listed for this component.<html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>
					<ns0:Guidance>
						The evaluator shall check the guidance documentation to ensure that it contains instructions to the
						administrator on how to ensure that only the allowed mechanisms are used in SSH connections with the TOE.<html:p /> 
					</ns0:Guidance>
					<ns0:Tests>
						The evaluator shall perform the following tests.  <html:p />
						If the TOE can be both a client and a server, these tests must be performed for both roles. 
						<ns0:testlist>
							<ns0:test>The evaluator must ensure that only claimed algorithms and cryptographic primitives are used to 
								establish an SSH connection. To verify this, the evaluator shall establish an SSH connection with a 
								remote endpoint. The evaluator shall capture the traffic exchanged between the TOE and the remote
								endpoint during protocol negotiation (e.g. using a packet capture tool or information provided by 
								the endpoint, respectively). The evaluator shall verify from the captured traffic that the TOE
								offers only the algorithms defined in the ST for the TOE for SSH connections. The evaluator shall
								perform one successful negotiation of an SSH connection and verify that the negotiated algorithms 
								were included in the advertised set. If the evaluator detects that not all algorithms defined in
								the ST for SSH are advertised by the TOE or the TOE advertises additional algorithms not defined in 
								the ST for SSH, the test shall be regarded as failed.<html:p />
								The data collected from the connection above shall be used for verification of the advertised
								hashing and shared secret establishment algorithms in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.5 and FCS_SSH_EXT.1.6 respectively. 
							</ns0:test>
							<ns0:test>For the connection established in Test 1, the evaluator shall terminate the connection and observe
								that the TOE terminates the connection.</ns0:test>
							<ns0:test>The evaluator shall configure the remote endpoint to only allow a mechanism that is not included in 
								the ST selection. The evaluator shall attempt to connect to the TOE and observe that the attempt fails.</ns0:test>
						</ns0:testlist><html:p />
					</ns0:Tests>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e5">
				<ns0:title>
					The TSF shall protect data in transit from modification, deletion, and insertion using: 
					<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">

						<ns0:selectable>hmac-sha2-256 (RFC 6668)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable>hmac-sha2-512 (RFC 6668)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>AEAD_AES_128_GCM (RFC 5647)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>AEAD_AES_256_GCM (RFC 5647)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>implicit </ns0:selectable>
					</ns0:selectables> and no other mechanisms.
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:note role="application">
					As described in RFC 5647, AEAD_AES_128_GCM and AEAD_AES_256_GCM need the corresponding encryption algorithm 
					to be selected. <html:p />
					In AES-GCM mode, integrity is not provided using a MAC, it is implicit in AES-GCM mode itself. There is no need
					for a corresponding FCS_COP element. The FCS_COP element for AES would already cover this. <html:p />
					If the negotiated encryption algorithm is one of the aes*-gcm@openssh.com algorithms, then the MAC field is 
					ignored during negotiation and implicitly selects AES-GCM for the MAC. “implicit” is not an SSH identifier and
					will not be seen on the wire; however, the negotiated MAC might be decoded as “implicit”.<html:p />
				</ns0:note>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator will check the description of the implementation of SSH in the TSS to ensure the hashing
						algorithms supported are specified. The evaluator will check the TSS to ensure that the hashing algorithms 
						specified are identical to those listed for this component. <html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>
					<ns0:Guidance>
						The evaluator shall check the guidance documentation to ensure that it contains instructions to the 
						administrator on how to ensure that only the allowed mechanisms are used in SSH connections with the TOE. <html:p />
					</ns0:Guidance>
					<ns0:Tests>
						<ns0:testlist>
							<ns0:test> The evaluator shall use the test data collected in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.4, Test 1 to verify that
								appropriate mechanisms are advertised.</ns0:test>
							<ns0:test> The evaluator shall configure an SSH peer to allow only a hashing algorithm that is not included
								in the ST selection. The evaluator shall attempt to establish an SSH connection and observe that 
								the connection is rejected.</ns0:test>
						</ns0:testlist><html:p />
					</ns0:Tests>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e6">
				<ns0:title>
					The TSF shall establish a shared secret with its peer using: 
					<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">

						<ns0:selectable>diffie-hellman-group14-sha256 (RFC 8268)</ns0:selectable>  
						<ns0:selectable>diffie-hellman-group15-sha512 (RFC 8268)</ns0:selectable>  
						<ns0:selectable>diffie-hellman-group16-sha512 (RFC 8268)</ns0:selectable>  
						<ns0:selectable>diffie-hellman-group17-sha512 (RFC 8268)</ns0:selectable>  
						<ns0:selectable>diffie-hellman-group18-sha512 (RFC 8268)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable>ecdh-sha2-nistp256 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable>ecdh-sha2-nistp384 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>ecdh-sha2-nistp521 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>  
						<ns0:selectable>curve25519-sha256 (RFC 8731)</ns0:selectable>
						<ns0:selectable>curve448-sha512 (RFC 8731)</ns0:selectable> 
					</ns0:selectables> and no other mechanisms.
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator will check the description of the implementation of SSH in the TSS to ensure the shared
						secret establishment algorithms supported are specified. The evaluator will check the TSS to ensure that
						the shared secret establishment algorithms specified are identical to those listed for this component.<html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>
					<ns0:Guidance>
						The evaluator shall check the guidance documentation to ensure that it contains instructions to the administrator 
						on how to ensure that only the allowed mechanisms are used in SSH connections with the TOE. <html:p />
					</ns0:Guidance>
					<ns0:Tests>
						<ns0:testlist>
							<ns0:test>The evaluator shall use the test data collected in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.4, Test 1 to verify that appropriate 
								mechanisms are advertised.</ns0:test>
							<ns0:test>The evaluator shall configure an SSH peer to allow only a key exchange method that is not included in the
								ST selection. The evaluator shall attempt to establish an SSH connection and observe that the
								connection is rejected.</ns0:test>
						</ns0:testlist><html:p />
					</ns0:Tests>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e7">
				<ns0:title>
					The TSF shall use <html:i>SSH KDF</html:i> as defined in 
					<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
						<ns0:selectable>RFC 4253 (Section 7.2)</ns0:selectable> 
						<ns0:selectable> RFC 5656 (Section 4) </ns0:selectable>
					</ns0:selectables>
					to derive the following cryptographic keys from a shared secret: <html:i>session keys</html:i>.
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:note role="application">
					RFC 4253 must be selected when the key establishment scheme (selected in FCS_SSH_EXT.1.6) uses finite field 
					cryptography (FFC) and RFC 5656 when it uses elliptic curve cryptography (ECC).  <html:p />
					RFC 4253 section 7.2 defines two KDFs for FFC based key establishment schemes.  Therefore RFC 4253 should be 
					selected if any of the RFC 4253 or RFC 8268 key establishment schemes are selected. <html:p />
					RFC 5656 section 4 defines KDFs used in ECC key establishment schemes and should be selected when RFC 5656 or 
					RFC 8731 key establishment schemes are selected.
				</ns0:note>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator will check the description of the implementation of SSH in the TSS to ensure the KDFs supported 
						are specified. The evaluator will check the TSS to ensure that the KDFs specified are identical to those listed 
						for this component.<html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:f-element id="fcs-ssh-ext-1e8">
				<ns0:title>
					The TSF shall ensure that 
					<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
						<ns0:selectable>a rekey of the session keys</ns0:selectable> 	 
						<ns0:selectable>connection termination</ns0:selectable>
					</ns0:selectables>
					occurs when any of the following thresholds are met: 
					<html:ul>
						<html:li>one hour connection time</html:li>
						<html:li>no more than one gigabyte of transmitted data, or</html:li>
						<html:li>no more than one gigabyte of received data.</html:li>
					</html:ul>
				</ns0:title>
				<ns0:note role="application">
					This SFR defines three thresholds that need to be implemented. These thresholds were arrived at to ensure 
					that the cryptographic key space for the symmetric session keys isn’t exhausted (more detail can be found in
					RFC 4344 and RFC 4253). A rekey or connection termination needs to be performed whenever a threshold is reached 
					for a given connection. The rekey applies to all session keys (encryption, integrity protection) for incoming and 
					outgoing traffic.  <html:p />
					It is acceptable for a TOE to implement lower thresholds than the maximum values defined in the SFR. If a 
					threshold is configurable, the guidance documentation needs to specify how to configure that threshold. <html:p />
					It is possible that hardware limitation may prevent reaching data transfer threshold in less than one hour. In 
					cases where data transfer threshold could not be reached due to hardware limitations it is acceptable to omit
					testing of this (SSH rekeying based on data transfer threshold). See Evaluation Activities for details.<html:p />
				</ns0:note>
				<ns0:aactivity level="element">
					<ns0:TSS>
						The evaluator shall check the TSS to ensure that if the TOE enforces connection rekey or termination limits
						lower than the maximum values that these lower limits are identified.  <html:p />
						In cases where hardware limitation will prevent reaching data transfer threshold in less than one hour, the
						evaluator shall check the TSS to ensure it contains: 
						<html:ol type="a">
							<html:li>An argument describing this hardware-based limitation and </html:li>
							<html:li>Identification of the hardware components that form the basis of such argument. </html:li>
						</html:ol>
						For example, if specific Ethernet Controller or Wi-Fi radio chip is the root cause of such
						limitation, these subsystems shall be identified.<html:p />
					</ns0:TSS>
					<ns0:Guidance>
						The evaluator shall check the guidance documentation to ensure that if the connection rekey or termination 
						limits are configurable, it contains instructions to the administrator on how to configure the relevant 
						connection rekey or termination limits for the TOE. <html:p />
					</ns0:Guidance>
					<ns0:Tests>
						The test harness needs to be configured so that its connection rekey or termination limits are greater than
						the limits supported by the TOE -- it is expected that the test harness should not be initiating the
						connection rekey or termination. <html:p />
						<ns0:testlist>
							<ns0:test>Establish an SSH connection.  Wait until the identified connection rekey limit is met.  Observed 
								that a connection rekey or termination is initiated.  This may require traffic to periodically be sent, 
								or connection keep alive to be set, to ensure that the connection is not closed due to an idle
								timeout. </ns0:test>
							<ns0:test>Establish an SSH connection.  Transmit data from the TOE until the identified connection rekey or
								termination limit is met.  Observe that a connection rekey or termination is initiated. </ns0:test>
							<ns0:test> Establish an SSH connection.  Send data to the TOE until the identified connection rekey limit or
								termination is met.  Observe that a connection rekey or termination is initiated.</ns0:test>
						</ns0:testlist><html:p />
					</ns0:Tests>
				</ns0:aactivity>
			</ns0:f-element>
			<ns0:audit-event type="optional">
				<ns0:audit-event-descr>Failure to establish SSH connection</ns0:audit-event-descr>
				<ns0:audit-event-info>Reason for failure.</ns0:audit-event-info>
				<ns0:audit-event-info type="optional">Non-TOE endpoint of attempted connection (IP Address)</ns0:audit-event-info>
			</ns0:audit-event>
			<ns0:audit-event type="optional">
			<ns0:audit-event-descr>Establishment of SSH connection</ns0:audit-event-descr>
				<ns0:audit-event-info type="optional">Non-TOE endpoint of connection (IP Address)</ns0:audit-event-info>
			</ns0:audit-event>
			<ns0:audit-event type="optional">
				<ns0:audit-event-descr>Termination of SSH connection session</ns0:audit-event-descr>
				<ns0:audit-event-info type="optional">Non-TOE endpoint of connection (IP Address)</ns0:audit-event-info>
			</ns0:audit-event>
			<ns0:audit-event type="optional">
				<ns0:audit-event-descr>Dropping of packet(s) outside defined size limits</ns0:audit-event-descr>
				<ns0:audit-event-info type="optional">Packet size</ns0:audit-event-info>
			</ns0:audit-event>
		</ns0:f-component>



	
    <ns0:f-component cc-id="fcs_sshc_ext.1" name="SSH Protocol - Client" status="sel-based">
		<ns0:depends on="ssh-client" />       
		<ns0:f-element id="fcs-sshc-ext-1e1">
			<ns0:title>The TSF shall authenticate its peer (SSH server) using: 
				<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
					<ns0:selectable>using a local database by associating each host name with a public key corresponding to the following list:
						<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
							<ns0:selectable>ssh-rsa (RFC 4253)</ns0:selectable> 
							<ns0:selectable>rsa-sha2-256 (RFC 8332)</ns0:selectable> 
							<ns0:selectable>rsa-sha2-512 (RFC 8332)</ns0:selectable>
							<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp256 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>
							<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp384 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>
							<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp521 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>
							<ns0:selectable>ssh-ed25519 (RFC 8709)</ns0:selectable>
							<ns0:selectable>ssh-ed448 (RFC 8709)</ns0:selectable>
						</ns0:selectables>
					</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>a list of trusted certification authorities when the public key is in the following formats:
						<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
							<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable>  
							<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp384 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable>  
							<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp521 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable>  
							<ns0:selectable>x509v3-rsa2048-sha256  (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable>
						</ns0:selectables>
					</ns0:selectable>
				</ns0:selectables>
				as described in RFC 4251 section 4.1.
			</ns0:title>
			<ns0:note role="application">
				The local database may be implemented using any equivalent local storage mechanism.
			</ns0:note>
			<ns0:aactivity>
				<ns0:TSS>
					No activities.<html:p />
				</ns0:TSS>
				<ns0:Guidance>
					The evaluator shall check the guidance documentation to ensure that it contains instructions to the 
					administrator on how to ensure that only the allowed mechanisms are used in SSH connections with the TOE.<html:p />
				</ns0:Guidance>
				<ns0:Tests>
					The evaluator shall perform the following tests: 
					<ns0:testlist>
						<ns0:test>[conditional] If using a local database by associating each host name with its corresponding public 
							key, the evaluator shall configure the TOE with only a single host name and corresponding public key in
							the local database. The evaluator shall verify that the TOE can successfully connect to the host identified
							by the host name.</ns0:test>
						<ns0:test>[conditional] If using a local database by associating each host name with its corresponding public key,
							the evaluator shall configure the TOE with only a single host name and non-corresponding public key in 
							the local database. The evaluator shall verify that the TOE fails to connect to a host not identified by 
							the host name. </ns0:test>
						<ns0:test>[conditional] If using a local database by associating each host name with its corresponding public
							key, the evaluator shall try to connect to a host not configured in the local database. The evaluator 
							shall verify that the TOE either fails to connect to a host identified by the host name or there is a prompt
							provided to store the public key in the local database. </ns0:test>
						<ns0:test>[conditional] If using a list of trusted certification authorities, the evaluator shall configure the
							TOE with only a single trusted certification authority corresponding to the host. The evaluator shall 
							verify that the TOE can successfully connect to the host identified by the host name.</ns0:test>
						<ns0:test>[conditional] If using a list of trusted certification authorities, the evaluator shall configure the 
							TOE with only a single trusted certification authority that does not correspond to the host. The evaluator 
							shall verify that the TOE fails to the host identified by the host name.</ns0:test>
					</ns0:testlist><html:p />
				</ns0:Tests>
			</ns0:aactivity>
		</ns0:f-element>
       <ns0:audit-event />
    </ns0:f-component>



	
    <ns0:f-component cc-id="fcs_sshs_ext.1" name="SSH Protocol - Server" status="sel-based">
		<ns0:depends on="ssh-server" />
		<ns0:f-element id="fcs-sshs-ext-1e1"> 
			<ns0:title>The TSF shall authenticate itself to its peer (SSH Client) using:
				<ns0:selectables linebreak="yes">
					<ns0:selectable>ssh-rsa (RFC 4253)</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>rsa-sha2-256 (RFC 8332)</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>rsa-sha2-512 (RFC 8332)</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp256 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable> 
					<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp384 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>ecdsa-sha2-nistp521 (RFC 5656)</ns0:selectable> 
					<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable> 
					<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp384 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable> 
					<ns0:selectable>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-nistp521 (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>x509v3-rsa2048-sha256  (RFC 6187)</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>ssh-ed25519 (RFC 8709)</ns0:selectable>
					<ns0:selectable>ssh-ed448 (RFC 8709)</ns0:selectable>
				</ns0:selectables>.
			</ns0:title>
			<ns0:note role="application">
				These requirements relate to Server authenticating to the Client. The Client authenticating to the Server is covered
				in FCS_SSHC_EXT.1.1.
			</ns0:note>
			<ns0:aactivity>
				<ns0:TSS>
					No activites.<html:p />
				</ns0:TSS>
				<ns0:Guidance>
					The evaluator shall check the guidance documentation to ensure that it contains instructions to the administrator
					on how to ensure that only the allowed mechanisms are used in SSH connections with the TOE. <html:p />
				</ns0:Guidance>
				<ns0:Tests>
					The evaluator shall repeat Test 1 and Test 2 from FCS_SSH_EXT.1.4 for each of the authentication mechanisms 
					supported by the TOE.  <html:p />
					Next the evaluator shall configure the remote peer to only allow an authentication mechanism that is not included 
					in the ST selection. The evaluator shall attempt to connect to the TOE and observe that the attempt fails.<html:p />
				</ns0:Tests>
			</ns0:aactivity>
		</ns0:f-element>
		<ns0:audit-event />
	</ns0:f-component>
</ns1:cryptsup>

</ns1:Security_Functional_Requirements>
  



	
<ns0:appendix id="appendix-optional-plus" title="Optional Requirements">  

    
    
</ns0:appendix> 





    <ns0:appendix id="appendix-sel-based" title="Selection-Based Requirements"> 
       
    
    
    </ns0:appendix> 
	



	
   <ns0:bibliography>
		<ns0:entry id="bibGPOS">
			<ns0:tag>GPOSPP</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/Profile/Info.cfm?id=442">Protection Profile for General Purpose Operating Systems</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>
		<ns0:entry id="bibMDM">
			<ns0:tag>MDMPP</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/Profile/Info.cfm?id=428">Protection Profile for Mobile Device Management</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>
		<ns0:entry id="bibAppPP">
			<ns0:tag>AppPP</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/Profile/Info.cfm?id=429">Protection Profile for Application Software</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>
		<ns0:entry id="bibVirt">
			<ns0:tag>VirtPP</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/Profile/Info.cfm?id=408">Protection Profile for Virtualization</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibOpenssh">
			<ns0:tag>openssh-portable/ PROTOCOL</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://cvsweb.openbsd.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb/src/usr.bin/ssh/PROTOCOL?rev=1.31">OpenSSH's deviations and extensions (1.6 transport: AES-GCM) </html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC4251">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 4251</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4251">The Secure Shell (SSH) Protocol Architecture </html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC4252 ">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 4252 </ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4252">The Secure Shell (SSH) Authentication Protocol</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC4253">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 4253</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4253">The Secure Shell (SSH) Transport Layer Protocol</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC4254">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 4254</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4254">The Secure Shell (SSH) Connection Protocol</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC4256">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 4256</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4256.txt">Generic Message Exchange Authentication for the Secure Shell Protocol (SSH)</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC4344">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 4344</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4344">The Secure Shell (SSH) Transport Layer Encryption Modes</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC5647">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 5647</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5647">AES Galois Counter Mode for the Secure Shell Transport Layer Protocol</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC5656">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 5656</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5656">Elliptic Curve Algorithm Integration in the Secure Shell Transport Layer</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC6187">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 6187</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6187">X.509v3 Certificates for Secure Shell Authentication</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC6668">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 6668</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6668">SHA-2 Data Integrity Verification for the Secure Shell (SSH) Transport Layer Protocol</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC8268">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 8268</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8268">More Modular Exponentiation (MODP) Diffie-Hellman (DH) Key Exchange (KEX) Groups for Secure Shell (SSH)</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC8308">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 8308</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc8308.txt">Extension Negotiation in the Secure Shell (SSH) Protocol</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC8332">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 8332</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc8332.txt">Use of RSA Keys with SHA-256 and SHA-512 in the Secure Shell (SSH) Protocol</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC8709">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 8709</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8709">Ed25519 and Ed448 public key algorithms for the Secure Shell (SSH) protocol </html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
		<ns0:entry id="bibRFC8731">
			<ns0:tag>RFC 8731</ns0:tag>
			<ns0:description>
				<html:a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8731">Secure Shell (SSH) Key Exchange Method using Curve25519 and Curve448</html:a>
			</ns0:description>
		</ns0:entry>   
    </ns0:bibliography>
</ns0:Package>
